<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Archiving the &quot;Obscene&quot; in Latin America</title>
    <link href="https://zebjtort.github.io/eroticarchives/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://zebjtort.github.io/eroticarchives" />
    <updated>2022-03-18T13:34:44-06:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Zeb Tortorici</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://zebjtort.github.io/eroticarchives</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Visualizing the &quot;Obscene&quot; in Latin America, 1700-1955</title>
        <author>
            <name>Zeb Tortorici</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://zebjtort.github.io/eroticarchives/introduction-to-archiving-the-obscene.html"/>
        <id>https://zebjtort.github.io/eroticarchives/introduction-to-archiving-the-obscene.html</id>

        <updated>2022-03-18T13:34:44-06:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    This webpage aims to visualize primarily two components of my current monograph and digital archiving project, Archiving the "Obscene": Erotica, Pornography, and Censorship in Latin America, 1700-1955. &lt;div class="flourish-embed flourish-network" data-src="visualisation/9027782"&gt;&lt;script src="https://public.flourish.studio/resources/embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt; I envision that the final version will have at least 3 visualization components&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>This webpage aims to visualize primarily two components of my current monograph and digital archiving project, <em>Archiving the "Obscene": Erotica, Pornography, and Censorship in Latin America, 1700-1955</em>. </p>
<p> </p>
<p>&lt;div class="flourish-embed flourish-network" data-src="visualisation/9027782"&gt;&lt;script src="https://public.flourish.studio/resources/embed.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</p>
<p>I envision that the final version will have at least 3 visualization components included on the website. They include:</p>
<ul>
<li>The first visualization component of my paper will be a web map, that uses a handful of eighteenth-century Mexican Inquisition records—in which certain individuals were prosecuted for owning, selling, or circulations “obscene” images and “immoral” objects, such as dolls, figurines, clocks, snuffboxes, and printed images—to think about the provenance and circulations of some of these objects. Of my corpus of several dozen Inquisition trials, what I have found interesting is that many of these “obscene” and “pornographic” images were purported to have been produced in France, and made their (often through Spain, New Granada, and the Caribbean) to Mexico. While I admittedly do not know how helpful it will be to geospatially map the traces of these circulations, I am interested in playing around with different <strong><u>mapping tools</u></strong> to get a better sense of how some of these objects circulated in the eighteenth century. I might also be interested in producing <strong><u>a Flourish network chart</u></strong> to think about some of the connections between France, Spain, Mexico, South America, and the Caribbean. (<em>The caveat: my data set is admittedly small since while I have access to several dozen Mexican Inquisition trials, only a handful of these actually go into detail about the provenance of the so-called obscene, immoral, and pornographic images and artifacts)</em>.</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<ul>
<li>The second visualization component will be stacked bar charts graphs representing a corpus of approximately 29 Mexican and Cuban stag films (i.e., silent black and white pornographic film shorts from the first half of the twentieth century) that are currently housed at the Filmoteca de la UNAM. I will (hopefully!) use <strong><u>OpenRefine</u></strong> to enter and standardize my data set (which will include information on the following: range of years of each film’s production; film reel format; information on language of film/intertitles; whether the film has closing credits, which though apocryphal, give us clues about production and/or pirating). I will then use <strong><u>Tableau Public</u></strong> to visualize some of this data. I am not yet sure how I want to proceed with this section, but I would like to see how I can visually represent uncertainty and ambivalence, along the lines of Johanna Drucker’s “Humanities Approaches to Graphical Display”). Lastly, I am potentially interested in (textually and possibly visually) tracing connections between film overlaps between the Filmoteca de la UNAM and the Kinsey Institute. What intrigues my about this project is that both archives hold some of the exact same stag films, but in no case are the films identical (that is, the version of the same film that ended up in both archives through radically difference provenance were edited, spliced, translated, and pirated differently).</li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<ul>
<li>The third and possibly final visualization component will be some version of text analysis, based on <strong><u>Voyant</u></strong>. This will be based on a handful of Spanish-language erotic novels published between 1900 and 1953, that have come to be preserved in the collections of a Mexico City community-based archives, Archivo El Insulto, in a box labeled “Caja Daniel” (“Daniel’s Box,” which was named after its previous owner, and contains 41 novels from that same time period). I am currently trying to use Spanish-language OCR to produce text files of some of these erotic novels, and I expect Voyant to be able to allow me to better visualize, in particular, the diversity of slang terms that refer to the body, sexuality, and desire. While I expect will be interested is being able to see, primarily through textual analysis and computational literary analysis (CLS), how terms relating to the body can partly help determine if particular texts are of Spanish, Cuban, Mexican, or Argentinian origins. <em>Note: below you will find some videos I linked to this website that speak to my long-term collaborative efforts with Archivo El Insulto. </em></li>
</ul>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p>See Archivo El Insulto below.  This is a grassroots queer archive that focuses on the preservation, display, and circulation of erotic materials that have circulated in Mexico over the course of the twentieth century: https://www.elinsulto.com</p>
<p> </p>
<p>The video below is an online conversation, in Spanish, between me and Michelle Davó and Adolfo Vega of Archivo El Insulto, through Moléculas Malucas: </p>
<figure class="post__video"><iframe loading="lazy" width="560" height="314" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/dBedL9eJ9vk" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" data-mce-fragment="1"></iframe></figure>
<p> </p>
<p>Below, please find a Facebook Live video conversation between me, Adolfo Vega, and Michelle Davó (of Archivo El Insulto), through the modern art museum, Museo Leonora Carrington in San Luis Potosí.  This was an event titled "<a href="https://www.facebook.com/watch/live/?extid=NS-UNK-UNK-UNK-IOS_GK0T-GK1C&amp;ref=watch_permalink&amp;v=4183134575099868" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Historia sobre la sexualidad en México en el Siglo XX</a>."</p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
